(
"ai_sub_version": "2.8.2",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 7,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 15,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "gemini-cli:gemini-3-flash-preview",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.1-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600,
"overwrite_system_prompt": false
),
"ollama_search": (
"key": "**********"
),
"web_search_tool": "ollama",
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": true,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": "libx264"
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"run": 3,
"max": 9,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false
)
ミラクル重大発表祭り
[Visual: Miracle Major Announcement Festival]
らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ
[Visual: Raden's New Outfit Reveal 3D Live]
いよーっ！
Iyo-!
漠然とした不安欲していた Fun
Vague anxiety, I was craving fun
日常に違和感？うんざりしていた
Did I feel out of place in daily life? I was sick of it
見慣れたありきたりな眺め
The usual scenery I was used to
理屈を超える変化を求めていた
I was looking for a change that would go beyond logic
窮屈で退屈な日々の中
In the midst of stifling and boring days
突然 キミは現れた
Suddenly, you appeared
全身の細胞 駆け巡るように
As if running through every cell in my whole body
走り出した未完成なストーリー
An unfinished story that started to run
モノクロだった景色が今
The scenery that was monochrome, now
キミと出会い カラフルに彩る Brand New World
Meeting you, it gets colored colorfully, Brand New World
ココロ奪われた
My heart was stolen
気まぐれな瞬間ハートビート
A capricious, momentary heartbeat
揺らぐ時空の狭間
In the gaps of wavering space-time
もうひとりじゃない煌めく星
I am not alone anymore, a shimmering star
描く未来予想図は
The future forecast I'm drawing
同じ夢を引き寄せたいよ
I want to draw the same dream together
果てしない旅路の向こうで
Beyond the endless journey
鳴り止まない ロマンが待っている
A romance that won't stop ringing is waiting
気づいた時にはね
When I realized it
I can't live without you
いつまでも キミと一緒なら
If I'm with you forever
ここから先 広がる宇宙
The universe that expands from here on
晴れ渡る空 飛び出して
Flying out into the clear sky
気分は上々 想像以上
My mood is top-notch, beyond imagination
机上の空論は終わりにして
Let's end the empty theories on paper
すべて叶える 絵空事
Making everything come true, a fantasy
時計の針が回り回る
The clock's hands spin and turn
限られた時の中で 鮮やかに Dancing Time
Vividly in limited time, Dancing Time
ココロ奪われた
My heart was stolen
気まぐれな瞬間ハートビート
A capricious, momentary heartbeat
揺らぐ時空の狭間
In the gaps of wavering space-time
もうひとりじゃない煌めく星
I am not alone anymore, a shimmering star
描く未来予想図は
The future forecast I'm drawing
同じ夢を引き寄せたいよ
I want to draw the same dream together
果てしない旅路の向こうに
Beyond the endless journey
紛れもない奇跡があるはず
There must be a clear miracle
さよならメランコリック
Goodbye, melancholic
止められはしない この衝動
I can't stop this impulse
突き進むだけさ
I'm just going to push forward
形振りかまわず Are you ready？
Without minding my appearance, are you ready?
限界はないさ 純度無限大の異次元
There is no limit, a dimension of infinite purity
散りばめた閃き 夜空 漲ってゆく
Scattered flashes, overflowing in the night sky
喜びは哀しみの倍 分かち合っていこう
Let's share joy twice as much as sadness
キミとならどこまでも
If I'm with you, anywhere.
レーザービーム
作詞・作曲：中田ヤスタカ
[Title: Laser Beam]
Lyrics & Composition: Yasutaka Nakata
ストレイト
Straight
ドキドキする
Heart pounding
視線はまるでレーザービーム
Your gaze is like a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing my heart with a swoosh
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
実る果実が水を弾いて
Ripe fruit bouncing off water
キラキラしてる光に似てる
Resembling sparkling light
グラウンドに立つキミの姿が
Your figure standing on the ground
まぶしくて 少し照れちゃうけど
Is so dazzling, it makes me blush a bit
ストレイト
Straight
まっすぐだね
You're so direct
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love is definitely a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing my heart with a swoosh
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
ふたりを繋ぐ 秘密の光
The secret light that connects us
あの日見つけた 秘密の光
The secret light we found that day
恋の瞬間 音は止まって
The moment of love, the sound stops
時間はスローリーに 恋の光線
And time goes slowly, a love beam of light
ストレイト
Straight
ドキドキする
Heart pounding
視線はまるでレーザービーム
Your gaze is like a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing my heart with a swoosh
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
いよーっ！
Iyooo!
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Step right up, come take a look!
始まりましたね！
It's started!
出囃子ジャポニズム
作詞・作曲：本多友紀 (Arte Refact)
[Title: Debayashi Japonism]
Lyrics & Comp: Yuki Honda (Arte Refact)
新衣装お披露目3Dライブ！
The new outfit reveal 3D live!
今夜はまだまだこれから！
Tonight is just beginning!
皆さん一緒に盛り上がっていきましょう！
Let's all get excited together!
尽きない好奇心
Curiosity that never ends
素晴らしきジャポニズムに触れて
Touching on the splendor of Japonism
令和の風雲児
The rising star of the Reiwa era
皆々にお届け致しましょう
We shall deliver it to everyone
饒舌に情熱
Passion in eloquence
伝えたい愛に溢れている
Overflowing with the love I want to convey
無知の知がきっと
Knowing that we know nothing will surely
素敵な始まりになるんだよ
Become a wonderful beginning
(もっと)知って
(More) I want you to know
(もっと)欲しい
(more)
たらふく味わって
Taste it until you've had your fill
(とことん)尊い
(Thoroughly) Precious
(とことん)人生
(thoroughly) life
紐解いた歴史に
Unraveled history
心惹かれていく
My heart is drawn to it
遥か遠く電波に乗ってあなたまで
Far away, riding the airwaves to reach you!
この想い純粋に伝えたい
I want to convey this feeling purely!
新しい世界
A brand new world
見せてあげる
I'll show it to you!
開口一番やっちゃって
First things first, let's get it started!
破天荒に型破って打ち立てる
Breaking the mold in an unprecedented way, we build!
金字塔パンチライン時を超え
A monumental punchline, crossing through time!
出囃子に乗せて
Riding on the entrance music
寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Step right up, come take a look!
はい！はい！
Hi! Hi!
はい！
Hi!
はい！はい！
Hi! Hi!
はい！
Hi!
浪漫を抱いた人生を
A life embraced by romance,
丸ごと賭けて傾きましょう
let's bet it all and behave extravagantly.
刹那に生きた足跡を
Footprints left in a fleeting moment,
偉大な先人と共に
along with our great predecessors.
洒落た口火切って
Striking a stylish spark,
手招く芸事の深淵
beckoning to the depths of the arts.
相反する感情
Conflicting emotions,
愛憎超えていく感動
a moving experience beyond love and hate.
遥か遠く世界超え宇宙まで
Far away, beyond the world and into space,
この想い果てしなく届けたい
I want to deliver these feelings endlessly!
オリエンタル
Oriental,
オクシデンタル
Occidental,
どちらも愛しちゃって
loving them both!
掻き立てる衝動が加速する
This stirring impulse accelerates,
創造の世界へと飛び込んで
diving into the world of creation.
小噺に乗せて
Set to a short story,
寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Come one, come all, gather 'round!
語り継いでく人世の想い
Handing down the feelings of this mortal world,
あなたの心に寄り添って
nestling close to your heart.
道楽主義で
With a hedonistic spirit,
小粋にいなせ
dashing and stylish.
そんな生き様如何ですか？
How do you like this way of life?
遥か遠く電波に乗ってあなたまで
Carried on airwaves far away to you,
この想い純粋に伝えたい
I want to convey these pure feelings.
新しい世界
A brand new world,
見せてあげる
I'll show it to you.
開口一番やっちゃって
Starting off with a bang,
破天荒に型破って打ち立てる
unprecedented and rule-breaking!
金字塔パンチライン時を超え
A monumental punchline transcending time!
出囃子に乗せて
Set to the entrance music,
寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Come one, come all, gather 'round!
はい！はい！
Hi! Hi!
はい！
Hi!
はい！はい！
Hi! Hi!
はい、ということで... はい、ということで
Alright then... alright!
始まりました！
It has begun!
儒烏風亭らでん 新衣装お披露目 3Dライブ！
Juufutei Raden's New Outfit Reveal 3D Live!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
はい、皆様改めてまして、こんばんは！
Alright, everyone, once again, good evening!
ホロライブデバイス、ReGLOSSの神出鬼没のミュージアム・プリンセス担当
From Hololive DEV_IS, ReGLOSS's elusive Museum Princess,
儒烏風亭一門は前座見習い、
and apprentice from the Juufutei school—
ちょっと待って(笑)
Wait a sec... (laughs)
儒烏風亭らでんでございます！
It is I, Juufutei Raden!
みんな来てくれて、ありがとうございます！
Thank you all for coming today!
本日のハッシュタグは、「#らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ」で
Today's hashtag is #RadenNewOutfitReveal3DLive.
いっぱいポストしてくれると、とっても嬉しいです。よろしくお願いします！
I'd be so happy if you post a lot. Please use it!
ちょっと待って、「大丈夫？」って言われてます。大丈夫です！ありがとうございます。
Wait, everyone's asking "Are you okay?" I'm fine! Thank you.
さあ今回ね、らでん3Dお披露目ライブ...
So, for this Raden 3D reveal live...
新衣装お披露目ライブ「ミラクル重大発表祭り！」
The new outfit reveal live: "Miracle Huge Announcement Festival!"
タイトルにもある通り、何やら重大発表が
As the title suggests, there are some huge announcements...
あるとか、ないとか。しかも、一つだけじゃないの！
Maybe! And there's more than just one!
ということでね、今日はぜひ最後までお楽しみください！
So, please stay tuned until the very end!
さあそして皆様、気になってますよね？
Now then, everyone, I'm sure you're curious,
この新衣装、いかがですか？
What do you think of this new outfit?
どう？みんなどうかな？これが私、らでんの新衣装、
Well? How is it, everyone? This is my new outfit,
ミュージアム・プリンセス衣装です！どう？
The "Museum Princess" outfit! What do you think?
どうかな？みんな。ちょっとね、今日ラグがあってね...
How is it? There's a bit of lag with the comments today...
「良い？」「良い？」ありがとう！ありがとうございます。
"Good?" "It's good?" Thank you! Thank you so much!
「可愛い」ありがとう！ありがとうございます。
"Cute!" Thank you! Thank you!
今回ですね、100万人記念ということで、
This time, to commemorate 1 million subscribers,
佐倉しおり先生にお仕立ていただきました！
the outfit was designed by Sakura Shiori-sensei!
これもね、普段から応援してくださっている皆様のおかげです。本当にありがとう！
This is all thanks to your continued support. Truly, thank you!
もちろんね、このライブのあと、アンコールライブっていうのがメン限であるんですけど、
Of course, after this, we'll have an encore live for members,
そこでまたのんびりと、このお衣装について詳しくね、見ていきたいと思いますので、
where we'll take a more relaxed, detailed look at this outfit.
待ってた方はぜひ、メンバーシップの方に加入していただければと思います。
For those of you who were waiting, please consider joining the membership.
今日ね、お昼ぐらいにメンバーの方が使えるスタンプも追加されましたので、
Today, around noon, we added some stamps that members can use,
ぜひコメント欄でよかったら使ってみてください。
so please feel free to use them in the comments if you'd like.
もうみんな使いたくてたまらない、アロワナスタンプとかが追加されてるんで、
The Arowana stamps that everyone's been dying to use have been added,
ぜひ皆さんでね、コメント欄いっぱいアロワナを泳がせてください。よろしくお願いします。
so please fill the comment section with swimming Arowanas. Thank you!
さあ、ということで。
Alright then.
お衣装、改めて新衣装なんですが、
Regarding the outfit, once again, this is my new look,
今回、衣装の他にもですね、
but this time, besides the outfit itself,
ちょっとね、ひとつ、とあるものを作りましたよ！
I've actually made something special!
ま、楽曲中にもね、出てきたんですけれども。
Well, it did make an appearance during the song earlier.
じゃんじゃかじゃんじゃか、あ、逆、あ、あ、じゃーん！
Ta-da, ta-da... Oh, wrong way... and ta-da!
ステッキでございます！
It's a stick!
素敵でございます！
It's wonderful! (Suteki!)
いいでしょう、これ。カッコいいでしょう。
Isn't it great? It looks cool, right?
今回ね、特注で素敵、作っちゃった！
I had this 'Suteki' custom-made for the occasion!
しかも！これだけじゃないんですよ！
And! That's not all!
見ててね。
Watch this.
らでんビーーーーーム！！
Raden Beeeeeam!!
うわあ！レーザービームだ！すごい！
Whoa! A laser beam! Amazing!
今回ね、レーザービームを出せるようにしてもらいました。
I had them set it up so I can fire a laser beam.
もう大丈夫です。
I'm okay now.
疲れちゃった。
I'm worn out.
いかん、今日ライブまだまだこれからですので、
No, the live show is still just getting started,
体力は温存していかないと。
I need to conserve my energy.
でも今日は、自分の体力がもう空っぽになるまで、
But today, until my energy is completely spent,
全力でライブするから、みんな応援よろしくね！
I'll give it my all, so please keep supporting me!
それでは、そろそろ、
Well then, it's about time...
次の曲に行きたいと思います！
...to move on to the next song!
さ、次の曲は何なのか、
Now, what will the next song be,
重大発表とは何なのか、
and what is this big announcement?
わくわくしながら聞いてくださいね。
Please look forward to it.
そしてここからは、
And from this point on,
ゲストも登場します！
guests will also be appearing!
ゲストパートは収録になりますので、悪しからず。
The guest segment is pre-recorded, so please keep that in mind.
それでは、今宵はまだまだ始まったばかり、
Well then, the night is still young,
みんなで一緒に楽しみましょう！
so let's all have a great time together!
それでは、どうぞ！
And now, here we go!
そう高く
Stretching so high,
果てなく
without an end,
明日へと導くよ
guiding the way to tomorrow,
私だけの光放ちたい
I want to shine with my very own light,
DIVE!
WOW WOW WOW WOW...
自信なくして ただ心に鍵かけて
Losing my confidence, I just locked up my heart,
響く自分の声に
and to my own resounding voice,
耳塞いでた
I had shut my ears.
ホントはいつだってわかっていたんだよ
But actually, I've always known it all along,
一番大切なものここにあること
that the most important thing is right here.
無限に広がる宇宙(そら)迷わず進もう
In the infinitely expanding sky, I'll advance without hesitation.
Go! Fly!
Yes! So High!
目を閉じて言い聞かせてみたってもう
Even if I close my eyes and try to tell myself,
カラダ中騒いでる止まらない Heart
it's already clamoring inside my body, my Heart won't stop,
強く熱く…！！
strongly and passionately...!!
そう高く 果てなく抱きしめた
Stretching so high, endlessly embracing the...
未来が軌跡になる
...future, it becomes a path.
生まれた思いが明日へと導くよ
These newborn feelings will guide me to tomorrow,
私だけの光放ちたい DIVE！
I want to shine with my very own light, DIVE!
WOW WOW WOW WOW...
誰のものでもない心に問いかけて
Asking my heart that belongs to no one else,
選んだ道の先へとまっすぐに
straight ahead on the path I've chosen.
どんな時だって見失わないよ
No matter when, I won't lose sight of it,
一番大切な場所を見つけたから
because I've found the place most important to me.
遠回りでもいい胸張って進もう
It's okay to take a detour, I'll move forward with pride.
Louder! Sing!
Louder!
不器用かなでも 傷ついたって構わないよ
I might be clumsy, but I don't care if I get hurt,
曇りない気持ちで生きたい Pride
I want to live with unclouded feelings, Pride,
私らしく…！！
true to myself...!!
両手を広げて解き放した昨日が
Spreading my arms, the 'yesterdays' I set free,
翼になる
will become wings.
重ねた出会いが...
These overlapping encounters...
...君と出会い
...Since meeting you,
からふるり彩ろう
everything's colored in.
心を奪われた気まぐれな瞬間ハートビート
My heart was stolen in a whimsical moment, heartbeat.
よろしくの狭間 もう一人じゃない
In the space of 'Nice to meet you', I'm not alone anymore.
諦める未来予想図は同じ
The future I'd given up on, the vision's the same.
夢を引き寄せたよ
I've drawn my dreams close.
果てしない旅路の向こうで
Beyond the endless journey,
鳴り止まないロマンが待っている
a never-ending romance awaits.
傷ついた時にはね
When I'm feeling hurt,
いつまでも君と一緒なら
as long as I'm with you forever,
ここから先広がる
it'll spread out from here...
空高く
High in the sky,
果てしなく
and boundlessly,
抱きしめた未来が
the future I embraced
奇跡になる
becomes a miracle.
生まれた
These born
思いが
feelings
明日へと導くよ
will lead the way to tomorrow.
私だけの光
A light that's mine alone,
放ちたい
I want to set it free.
WOW WOW WOW...
JAPANの美術史♪ (Art! Art!)
Japanese Art History♪ (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (絵画に立体！)
Japanese Art History♪ (Painting and Sculpture!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (テストもバッチリ！)
Japanese Art History♪ (Ace that test!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!
Let's learn it SHOW!
さあ、3Dライブの途中ではございますが...
Now, even though we're in the middle of a 3D live...
ここで日本美術史の授業を始めたいと思います
I'd like to start a Japanese art history lesson right here!
は～いみなさんこんにちは！美術史を学ぶ時間です！
Hello everyone! It's time to learn art history!
まずは縄文・弥生・古墳まで やってみよう
First, let's cover Jomon, Yayoi, and Kofun!
火焔型土器
Flame-style pottery,
遮光器土偶
Goggle-eyed figurine,
縄文のビーナス！
Venus of Jomon!
銅鐸、銅戈、銅矛、銅剣、弥生土器
Dotaku, Doka, Doko, Doken, Yayoi pottery!
埴輪も色々、踊る人々、掛甲武人、馬型埴輪
Various Haniwa: Dancing People, Warrior, and Horse types!
古墳出土の鉄刀、鉄剣、七支刀に土師器 須恵器
Kofun iron swords, Seven-branched sword, Hajiki and Sueki!
OK OK OK OK OK いい感じ！
OK OK OK OK OK, looking good!
次は飛鳥に奈良時代！ 3! 2! 1! GO!
Next up: Asuka and Nara periods! 3! 2! 1! GO!
仏像いっぱい釈迦如来、菩薩と合わせて三尊像
Statues of Shaka Nyorai, and the Bodhisattva Triads!
玉虫厨子、天寿国繍帳、金堂壁画、古墳壁画
Tamamushi Shrine, Tenjukoku Mandara, Kondo and Kofun murals!
東大寺には奈良の大仏、興福寺には阿修羅像
The Great Buddha at Todai-ji, and Ashura at Kofuku-ji!
音と一緒に遊びましょう！螺鈿紫檀五絃琵琶
Let's play with sound! The Raden Shitan Five-stringed Lute!
未来のキミに届くように
So that it reaches the future you,
繋いでいこう この想い
let's connect these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there's love, it'll be okay,
語り合う朝が来るまで
until the morning we talk together comes.
JAPANの美術史♪ (Art! Art!)
Japanese Art History♪ (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (絵画に立体！)
Japanese Art History♪ (Painting and Sculpture!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (テストもバッチリ！)
Japanese Art History♪ (Ace that test!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!
Let's learn it SHOW!
まだまだ色々ございます 頑張ってついてきてくださいね
There's still plenty more! Please try to keep up!
平安 鎌倉 南北朝 参る
Heian, Kamakura, Nanboku-cho... Here we go!
曼荼羅、一木造り、寄木造り
Mandala, Ichiboku-zukuri, Yosegi-zukuri!
鳥獣人物戯画に源氏物語
Choju-giga and The Tale of Genji!
平等院鳳凰堂阿弥陀如来坐像
The Seated Amida Buddha of the Phoenix Hall!
模様がとってもかわいい
The pattern is so very cute!
片輪車螺鈿手箱！
The Katawaguruma Raden Cosmetic Box!
東大寺の南大門の金剛力士像
The Kongo Rikishi statues of Todai-ji's Nandaimon!
阿弥陀二十五菩薩来迎図、山越阿弥陀図
Amida's Descent and Amida Rising over the Mountains!
蒙古襲来絵詞、空也上人像
The Mongol Invasions scrolls, and Priest Kuya!
一遍上人絵伝、後三年合戦絵巻
Ippen Shonin's biography, and the Later Three Years' War scrolls!
YOYO! 半分くらい来たぜ多分！
YOYO! We're about halfway through, probably!
まだまだいくぜ、ありのまま 室町から安土桃山！
Keep 'em coming, as they are! From Muromachi to Azuchi-Momoyama!
能面 翁に 枯山水 天橋立図 呂洞賓図
Okina mask, Zen gardens, Amanohashidate, and Lu Dongbin!
狩野派の屏風！
Kano school folding screens!
曜変天目茶碗
Yohen Tenmoku tea bowl!
洛中洛外図屏風
Scenes In and Around Kyoto screen!
唐獅子図屏風、松鷹図
Chinese Lions screen and Hawks in Pines!
職人尽図、花下遊楽図、松林図、山水図
Craftsmen, Merrymaking, Pine Trees, and Landscapes!
八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱 本物だー！
The Yatsuhashi Raden Writing Box! It's the real thing!
未来のキミに届くように
So that it reaches the future you,
繋いでいこう この想い
let's connect these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there's love, it'll be okay,
語り合う朝が来るまで
until the morning we talk together comes.
と、なんと今回特別に バーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱さんに来ていただきました！
And now, as a special treat, the Virtual Yatsuhashi Writing Box is here!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you very much!
さあ、最後、江戸時代から昭和まで！ 行きますよ！
Now for the finale, from Edo to Showa! Here we go!
3! 2! 1! GO!
舟橋蒔絵硯箱、風神雷神図屏風
Funabashi Writing Box, Wind and Thunder Gods screen!
燕子花図屏風、見返り美人
Irises screen and Beauty Looking Back!
好色一代男、奥の細道
Life of an Amorous Man, Narrow Road to the Deep North!
The Life of an Amorous Man, The Narrow Road to the Deep North
富嶽三十六景、東海道中膝栗毛
Thirty-six Views of Mount Fuji, Tokaidochu Hizakurige
老猿、ゆあみ、坑夫
Old Monkey, The Bath, The Miner
墓守、伎芸天
The Grave Keeper, Gigeiten
竜虎図、黒き猫
Dragon and Tiger, Black Cat
鮭、海の幸
Salmon, Harvest of the Sea
渡頭の夕暮れ
Sunset at the Ferry
麗子微笑、紫禁城
Reiko Smiling, The Forbidden City
班猫、五浦釣人
Tabby Cat, The Fisherman at Izura
太陽の塔
Tower of the Sun
吉原治良の円
Jiro Yoshihara's Circle
東山魁夷の道
Kaii Higashiyama's Road
未来のキミに届くように
So it reaches the future you
繋いでいこう この想い
Let's connect these feelings
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there's love, it'll be okay
語り合おう 朝が来るまで
Let's talk until morning comes
未来まで
Until the future
JAPANの美術史♪ (アート！アート！)
JAPAN's Art History (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (絵画に立体！)
JAPAN's Art History (Paintings to 3D!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (テストもバッチリ！)
JAPAN's Art History (The test will be perfect too!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！
Let's learn!
ありがとう！
Thank you!
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんわ。
Good evening to everyone watching the live.
ライブの途中ではございますが、
Although we're in the middle of the live,
ここでらでんの小咄、美術解説の時間です！
it's time for Raden's short story and art commentary!
なんと今回ご紹介するのは、こちらでん！じゃじゃーん！
And what I'm introducing this time is this! Ta-da!
国宝 八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱！
National Treasure: Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako!
ということで、今回特別に東京国立博物館さんから
So, we've specially borrowed
3Dモデルをお借りしましたー！
a 3D model from the Tokyo National Museum!
よいしょ、みんなにもよく見てもらいましょう。
Heave-ho, let's let everyone have a good look.
こちらでございます。
Here it is.
こちらがバーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱です。
This is the Virtual Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako.
螺鈿ってなんかどっかで聞いたことがありますね。
Raden... I feel like I've heard that somewhere before.
なんかそんな名前のバーチャルユーチューバーがいるような、いなかったような。
Like there's a VTuber with that name, or maybe not.
こちらは私のオリジナル曲「JAPANの美術史 お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW」にも登場する作品です。
This is a work that also appears in my original song "JAPAN's Art History: Let's Learn!"
どうですか皆さん、この輝きとデザイン！
What do you think of this shine and design, everyone?
大胆かつ、花びらの装飾の細かい部分も美しいこちらの作品。
This work is bold, and the fine details of the petal decorations are also beautiful.
作ったのは、尾形光琳という人です。
The person who made it was Ogata Korin.
彼がこの硯箱を作ったのは江戸時代なんですが、
He created this inkstone case in the Edo period,
どこかモダンな要素も感じることができます。
but you can feel some modern elements in it.
さて、工芸品を見るとき様々な見方がありますが、
Now, there are various ways to look at crafts,
手助けになるのは作品名です。
but the work's title is a great help.
ではスライド行きます。
Now, let's move to the slide.
えー、この工芸品の名前、復習しましょう。
Let's review the name of this craft.
八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱。
Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako.
漢字がたくさん入っていますが、一つ一つ紐解いていきましょう。
It's full of kanji, but let's break them down one by one.
まずは「八橋」。
First, "Yatsuhashi."
日本美術史における工芸品は、物語の一場面や
In Japanese art history, crafts are often themed around
和歌、歌ですね、がテーマになっていることが少なくありません。
a scene from a story or a waka—a poem.
そしてこの硯箱もその一つ。
And this inkstone case is one of them.
伊勢物語 第九段 三河の国 八橋の場面が主題になっているんですよ。
The theme is the Yatsuhashi scene from Section 9 of "The Tales of Ise," in Mikawa Province.
なのでこれは橋ですね。
So, these are bridges.
八橋、この場面に出てくる八つの橋のこと。
Yatsuhashi refers to the eight bridges that appear in this scene.
つまりは何を描いたかを表しています。
In other words, it represents what was depicted.
では、何を描いたかが分かったら次に、
Now that we know what was depicted, next is
どんな技法が使われたか。
what techniques were used.
それを表すのが「蒔絵」、そして「螺鈿」です。
Those are represented by "Makie" and "Raden."
蒔絵とは、簡単に言うと金の粉を
Simply put, Makie is gold powder applied
漆という接着剤を用いて貼り付けたもの。
using lacquer as an adhesive.
ここでいうと、カキツバタの葉っぱの部分ですね。
In this case, it's the leaves of the rabbit-ear irises.
ピンピンってなってる部分です。
The parts that are sticking up.
次に、螺鈿とは、貝の光沢を持つ部分を
Next, Raden is the iridescent part
薄くして貼り付けたもの。
of a shell, thinned and applied.
ここでいうと、カキツバタのお花の部分です。
In this case, it's the flowers of the rabbit-ear irises.
この作品に使われているのはアワビ貝で、花びらを表現するために、
Abalone shells are used in this work, and to represent the petals,
あえて穴の開いた貝を使用しているのが分かります。
you can see that shells with holes were deliberately used.
そして最後に、そもそもこれは何か。
And finally, what is this object in the first place?
それを表すのが「硯箱」です。
That's represented by "Suzuribako."
真ん中ご覧ください、こちら。
Look at the center, here.
墨汁を作る硯入れが、上の段にあり...
The inkstone tray for making ink is on the upper level...
さらにその段の下、
And below that,
下の段は料紙、紙入れになっています。
the lower level is for ryoshi, or paper.
さあ、これで「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」の言葉の紐解きが完了しましたね。
Now, we've finished breaking down the term "Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Suzuribako."
カキツバタが咲く川に架かる橋のダイナミックな魅力にも大注目なこの硯箱。
Pay close attention to the dynamic charm of the bridges over the river where irises bloom.
パカっと開けると、波が描かれています。
When you pop it open, waves are depicted.
もうここまで聞いたら、なぜそこに波の意匠を施したのか、皆さんならお分かりですね。
Having heard this much, I'm sure you all understand why the wave design was applied there.
...の段にある橋の下の波、ということでございますね。
...the waves under the bridge on that level, you see.
実はですね、こちらの八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱、普段展示される際は箱を閉じた状態なわけなんですよ。
Actually, this Yatsuhashi Makie Raden inkstone box is usually displayed with its lid closed.
つまり、中の様子をご覧いただけるのは...
In other words, being able to see the inside like this...
...この配信ならではの貴重な機会です！
...is a precious opportunity unique to this stream!
こちらがなんと、2026年5月26日から8月16日、
And surprisingly, from May 26 to August 16, 2026,
本館2室にて展示されるとのことで、
it will be on display in Gallery 2 of the Honkan.
東京国立博物館さんでぜひ見てみていただければと思います！
I hope you'll go see it at the Tokyo National Museum!
このね、波のね、細かいところが、これ筆でやってるんですからね。
Look at these fine details of the waves; they were all done with a brush.
筆でこうやって... あ、お時間となってしまいました。
Working with a brush like this... Ah, my time is up.
それでは皆さんまた次回お会いいたしましょう！
Well then, everyone, I'll see you all next time!
特報 その①
[Special News Part 1]
2027年1月 儒烏風亭らでんと東京国立博物館コラボ決定！
[Jan 2027: Juufuutei Raden x Tokyo National Museum Collab Confirmed!]
ということでなんと！私、儒烏風亭らでんと、
And so, believe it or not! A collaboration between me,
東京国立博物館さんとのコラボが決定しましたー！！
Juufuutei Raden, and the Tokyo National Museum has been confirmed!!
すごーい！みんなやったよー！
It's amazing! Everyone, we did it!
らでん配信とか、もういろんなところで東博さんがずっと大好きだって言ってたんですけども...
I've been saying in my streams and all over the place how much I love Tohaku...
今回、念願の東博・らでんコラボでございます！すごーい！
And now, it's the long-awaited Tohaku-Raden collab! Incredible!
あら、東博、最近名前聞きましたね。そうです。
Oh, you've heard the name 'Tohaku' recently? That's right.
先日ね、10月から京都、1月から東京にて開催予定の特別展『源氏物語』展の...
It was recently announced that I'll be doing a special track for the audio guide...
音声ガイドのスペシャルトラックを務めさせていただくことが発表されましたが...
...of the 'The Tale of Genji' exhibition starting in Kyoto in Oct and Tokyo in Jan...
なんと、この特別展『源氏物語』展の東京会場となる、
...and surprisingly, with the Tokyo venue for this 'Genji' exhibition,
東京国立博物館さんとのコラボが決定いたしました！すごーい！
the collab with the Tokyo National Museum has been confirmed! Amazing!
開催時期はこの『源氏物語』展と同じ、2027年1月に...
The collaboration is scheduled for January 2027,
実施予定となっております！
the same time as the 'The Tale of Genji' exhibition!
なんで、こっちは『源氏物語』展・らでんコラボ、
So, we'll have the 'The Tale of Genji' Raden collab,
そして同じ1月に、東博・らでんコラボがあると！
and in the same January, a Tokyo National Museum Raden collab!
もっと簡単に言うと、来年の1月は東博の色んなところに...
To put it simply, Raden-chan will be appearing all over
らでんちゃんが出没しちゃいまーす！っていう感じです。
Tohaku next January! That's how it's going to be.
こちら詳細はですね、また続報をお待ちいただければと思います。
Please wait for further updates regarding the details.
すごいでしょー！すごーい！
Incredible, right? So amazing!
ということで、本日の重大発表一つ目は、東博・らでんコラボでございました！
So, the first big announcement for today was the Tohaku-Raden collaboration!
みんなありがとー！！
Thank you, everyone!!
さあ、ライブも重大発表もまだまだ続きます。
Now, the live and the big announcements continue.
ちょっと待って、ちょっと疲れちゃった（笑）
Wait a sec, I'm a bit tired (laughs).
ということでね、東博、元々らでんが日本美術史に興味持ったのって、
Anyway, my interest in Japanese art history actually started
東博さんで能面を見て、その時に、『あぁ、なんて美しいんだ』って思ったし、
when I saw a Noh mask at Tohaku and thought, 'Oh, how beautiful.'
日本で生まれ育ったのに日本のこと本当に何も知らないんだなって思ったのがきっかけで、
I realized that even though I was born and raised in Japan, I really knew nothing about it.
そっから、なんやかんやって日本美術史勉強したりして、
From there, one thing led to another, I studied art history,
なんやかんやってホロライブに入って、
one thing led to another and I joined Hololive...
なんやかんやって今こんな素敵なお衣装をお披露目して、
...one thing led to another and I'm showing off this wonderful outfit...
なんやかんやってこんなありがたいコラボをさせていただけることになりました！
...and now I'm getting to do this incredible collaboration!
みんなのおかげだよ、ありがとー！！
It's all thanks to you. Thank you!!
もう人生本当に何が起こるか分かりません。何がどう未来へ繋がっていくのか、
You really never know what will happen in life. It's unbelievable.
みたいなことももう分かりません。人生は奇妙な冒険みたいなもんでございますな。
I have no idea how things will connect to the future. Life is like a bizarre adventure.
さあ、ということでそろそろ次の曲に行きたいと思います。
Well then, it's about time to move on to the next song.
それでは聞いてください。『ココロパズルリズム』。
Please listen: 'Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm'.
これからの未来 ほらたくさんのピース
The future ahead, see, so many pieces
組み立てるのはキミしだい
It's up to you to put them together
一つずつの明日を生きる
Living each tomorrow
ココロパズルリズム
[Song: Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm]
vocal: 儒烏風亭らでん
illustration: ちぼみるく
Vocal: Jofutei Raden
Illustration: Chibomiru
mix: 赤ティン
movie: 金子開発
Mix: Akatin
Movie: Kaneko Kaihatsu
これからの未来 ほらたくさんのピース
In this future, look at all the pieces
組み立てるのはキミしだい
It's up to you to put them together
一つずつの明日を生きる
Living each tomorrow one by one
ココロのパズルとリズム
The puzzle and rhythm of the heart
うまくは言えないけど
I can't say it well, but the feeling
不思議と安心していられる感覚って
Of being strangely at peace
まるでパズルみたいだ
It's just like a puzzle
もうずっと前から僕らは予約席
We've had reserved seats for a long time
さあ両手つないで
Come on, hold both hands
きっと一つになれる
And we can surely become one
完成が見えていても
Even if you can see it's complete
すんなりとはいかないね
It doesn't go smoothly, does it?
それぞれが夢のカケラだね
Each one is a piece of a dream
これからの未来 ほらたくさんのピース
In this future, look at all the pieces
組み立てるのはキミしだい
It's up to you to put them together
一つずつの明日を生きる
Living each tomorrow one by one
空いた隙間を埋める
Filling the empty gaps
楽しいことも きっとあるけど
There will surely be fun times too
それよりも 大切なのは
But what's more important than that
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
Is when you're sad or happy
一緒に泣ける
Being able to cry together
そんなココロノパズル
That kind of heart's puzzle
すんなりとはいかないね
It doesn't go smoothly, does it?
キミと僕のパズルの行方も
The whereabouts of your and my puzzle too
これからのLOVE STORY
This future love story
ほらたくさんのピース
Look at all the pieces
間違えることもあるけど
Sometimes you make mistakes, but
胸に刻み明日を生きる
Engraving it in your heart, live tomorrow
空いた隙間を埋める
Filling the empty gaps
楽しいことも きっとあるけど
There will surely be fun times too
それよりも 大切なのは
But what's more important than that
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
Is when you're sad or happy
一緒に泣ける
Being able to cry together
そんなココロノリズム
That kind of heart's rhythm
don't cry don't cry
Walk hand in hand
ah ah 繋いで
Ah ah, holding on
it's a nice day
これからの未来 ほらたくさんのピース
In this future, look at all the pieces
組み立てるのはキミしだい
It's up to you to put them together
一つずつの明日を生きる
Living each tomorrow one by one
空いた隙間を埋める
Filling the empty gaps
楽しいことも きっとあるけど
There will surely be fun times too
それよりも 大切なのは
But what's more important than that
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
Is when you're sad or happy
一緒に泣ける
Being able to cry together
そんなココロノパズル
That kind of heart's puzzle
ココロノリズム
Heart's rhythm
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは！
Good evening to everyone watching the live stream!
ライブの途中ではございますが、
We're in the middle of the live performance,
ここでらでんの小噺美術解説のお時間です！
but it's time for Raden's little art commentary!
今回ご紹介するのは...
The piece I'll be introducing today is...
「こちらで」
Here it is!
「じゃじゃーん！」
Ta-da!
クロード・モネ 「睡蓮の池」
Claude Monet: "The Water-Lily Pond"
今回なんと、ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております。本当にありがとうございます！
Today, we have borrowed this image from the National Gallery in London. Thank you so much!
皆さんどうですか？
What do you all think?
私モネの描く世界が大好きなんです。
I absolutely love the world Monet paints.
まあモネといえば日本でもとても人気の高い画家ですが、彼の絵画の魅力はどのようなところにあるのでしょうか。
Monet is a very popular painter in Japan, but what exactly is the charm of his paintings?
今回は彼の絵画に内在する魅力を言語化していきましょう！
Today, let's put the inherent charm of his paintings into words!
この作品は1899年頃描かれました。
This work was painted around 1899.
緑色の光が溢れる睡蓮の池には、大きな橋が架かり、橋の奥には柳が描かれています。
In the water-lily pond filled with green light, a large bridge spans across with willows in the background.
実はこの場所、モネの自宅に作った池なんです。
Actually, this place is a pond Monet created at his own home.
フランスのジヴェルニーという町に家を購入した彼は、近隣の川から水を引き、自分の理想とする庭を作りました。
After buying a house in Giverny, France, he drew water from a nearby river to create his ideal garden.
アーチ状の大きな橋。これいわゆる太鼓橋と呼ばれる橋と柳。
The large arched bridge. This is what's called a "drum bridge," and the willows...
あれ、なんだか日本っぽさを感じませんか？
Wait, doesn't it feel a bit Japanese?
それもそのはず。彼は日本の浮世絵に強く影響を受けた画家でした。
And for good reason. He was a painter strongly influenced by Japanese Ukiyo-e.
彼の描く絵は光に溢れていて、目の前で風が吹いて、水面が揺れているようにも見えます。
His paintings are filled with light; it's as if the wind is blowing and the water's surface is rippling right before you.
じーっと見ていると、水も花も木も橋も、空気でさえも溶けていくようです。見ていて落ち着く絵画だと思いませんか？
Looking closely, the water, flowers, trees, bridge, and even the air seem to melt away. Don't you think it's a calming painting?
モネは絵を描く時、色を混ぜて塗るのではなく、純粋な、何も混ざってない色を置くように塗りました。
When Monet painted, he didn't mix colors; he applied pure, unmixed colors as if placing them.
色は混ぜれば混ぜるほど、塗り重ねれば重ねるほど暗くなっていきます。
The more you mix or layer colors, the darker they become.
彼はこの課題を「色を置く」ことによって解決し、光に溢れた絵画の表現に成功したんです。
He solved this by "placing colors," succeeding in creating expressions filled with light.
この絵画に近づいてみると、筆跡がしっかり残っています。
Getting closer to this painting, the brushstrokes are clearly visible.
隣り合った絵具ひとつひとつの相乗効果を計算し、絵具の塊から温度感や湿度感を感じることができる風景へと変貌する表現は、モネが生涯かけて研究していたものです。
Calculating the synergy of each paint stroke to create a landscape where you feel temperature and humidity was Monet's lifelong research.
光を求めたモネが、陰影のない日本の浮世絵に強く惹かれたのも理解できますね。
It's easy to see why Monet, seeking light, was drawn to shadowless Japanese Ukiyo-e.
彼の絵画の明るさは画家としての研究の成果であり、情熱さえ感じられるそんな作品だと私は感じます。
The brightness of his paintings is the result of his research, and I feel his passion in such works.
みんなはこの絵画、どう読んだかな？
I wonder how all of you interpreted this painting?
実はモネは印象派の画家と呼ばれるきっかけを作った人でもあるんですが、それはまた別のお話。
Actually, Monet was the catalyst for the name "Impressionist," but that's a story for another time.
という感じでございましたね。こちらはロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて見ることができます。ぜひ行ってみてください！
And that's that. You can see this at the National Gallery in London. Please do visit!
また次回！
See you next time!
(I want to fight your brother)
(let's kung-fu)
Every night I look to the skies and wonder what we did
Always a naive point of view that breaks us in the end
If I could find the meaning of it all I'd take the chance
Maybe in time we'll walk the mile and change it if we can
It's now and always
(How did we get this far, did we get this far now?)
Always
(We're making a brand new start, just a brand new start now)
(Nothing will hold me down, never hold me down now)
Always
WAVE GOODBYE TO ME!
Around the world 新しいことに
Around the world, for something new
Around the world フミダスチカラで
Around the world, with the strength to take the first step
Around the world 世界は変わるさ
Around the world, the world will change
But don't run away 'cause if it's not ok!
I'll change that world into something better honey!
(let's kung-fu)
果てしなく広がる
Endlessly spreading out...
Limitlessly stretching...
この大地を
...across this vast land,
僕らはまた 歩き続けるさ
we will continue to walk on.
全ての意味が
If we could understand...
分かるのならば
...all of the meaning,
この瞳で
with these eyes,
何を見つめるのだろう
what would we gaze upon?
IT'S NOW AND ALWAYS
(HOW DID WE GET THIS FAR)
ALWAYS
(WE'RE MAKING A BRAND NEW START)
(NOTHING WILL HOLD ME DOWN)
ALWAYS
WAVE GOODBYE TO ME!
AROUND THE WORLD
君だけのために
Just for you alone
AROUND THE WORLD
探し続けるよ
I'll keep on searching
AROUND THE WORLD
奇跡のかけらを
For fragments of a miracle
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
Yeah ey AND YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE RAINING
AND YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE HARD
AS LONG AS WE TRUST EACH OTHER
NOTHING'S GONNA BREAK APART OH NO! NO!
IF YA WANNA BE SOMEBODY
GET UP ON YA FEET AND GO
I KNOW WE'RE GONNA MEET EACH OTHER
SOMEWHERE AROUND THE GLOBE
AROUND THE WORLD
いつでも自分に
For those who always...
AROUND THE WORLD
負けている人は
...lose to themselves,
AROUND THE WORLD
何も掴めない
they can grasp nothing at all.
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
I'LL CHANGE THAT WORLD INTO SOMETHING BETTER HONEY!
特報
[Breaking News]
その②
Part 2
儒烏風亭らでん × THE NATIONAL GALLERY, LONDON コラボ決定!!
Juufuutei Raden x THE NATIONAL GALLERY, LONDON
Collaboration Confirmed!!
When Raden Meets Art
儒烏風亭らでんの瞳に映る世界の名画
A SHARED ART JOURNEY
World Masterpieces Reflected in Juufuutei Raden's Eyes
はい、ということで！
Alright, so!
なんと私、儒烏風亭らでんと！
Incredibly, I, Juufuutei Raden, and...
ロンドン ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボが決定しました！
...the National Gallery in London
have a collaboration confirmed!
ナショナル・ギャラリーさんといえば、
Speaking of the National Gallery...
モネ、ゴッホ、ターナー... とにかく色んな画家さんたちの、
...Monet, Van Gogh, Turner... in short, many artists,
超有名な作品をいっぱい所蔵されているところなんですが...
and many of their super famous works are housed there.
なんとそんなナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ、
And now, this collaboration with the National Gallery,
『儒烏風亭らでんの瞳に映る世界の名画 - A SHARED ART JOURNEY -』
"World Masterpieces Reflected in Juufuutei Raden's Eyes
- A SHARED ART JOURNEY -"
コラボ決定です！すごーい！
The collaboration is confirmed! Amazing!
さあこれね、とある3つの名画とコラボしてるんですが、
みんなわかるかな？
Now, we're collaborating with three masterpieces.
Do you guys know them?
3つね、3つあるんだけど。
Three, there are three of them.
では、左からいきましょうか。
Well, let's start from the left.
左：ターナー『雨、蒸気、速度――グレート・ウェスタン鉄道』
Left: Turner's "Rain, Steam, and Speed
– The Great Western Railway".
そして、真ん中：モネの『睡蓮の池』
And in the middle: Monet's "The Water-Lily Pond".
そして、一番右。これは皆さんおわかりでしょう。
And on the far right. You all know this one.
ゴッホの『ひまわり』！
Van Gogh's "Sunflowers"!
そして今回、コラボ商品がございます。全8種類あるんですよ。
And this time, we have collaboration goods.
There are 8 types in total.
じゃあ、一つずつね、ちょっと紹介していきましょう。
So, let me introduce them one by one.
まず、左上からいきましょうか。
First, let's start from the top left.
まずはフレグランスミストセットです。
First is the fragrance mist set.
らでんが監修・考案したフレグランスミスト、
These fragrance mists, supervised and designed by Raden,
3点の名画が持つイメージを香りで表現しました。
express the image of the three masterpieces
through scent.
本商品はアルコールフリーのフレグランスミストなので、
Since these are alcohol-free fragrance mists,
色んな場面に合わせて使用可能です。
they can be used in various situations.
じゃあ、お隣いきましょうか。
Next, let's move to the next one.
そのお隣、ローラーボールペン。
The one beside it, rollerball pens.
3つの名画のエッセンスと儒烏風亭らでんの家紋を
Fusing the essence of the three masterpieces
見事に融合させたデザインでございます。
with Juufuutei Raden's crest in a beautiful design.
じゃあ次は、左下。カップ＆ソーサーセット。
Next, bottom left. Cup & saucer set.
描き下ろしイラストからインスピレーションを得た
Inspired by the newly drawn illustration,
ボーンチャイナ製のカップ＆ソーサーセットでございます。
this is a bone china cup & saucer set.
ソーサーの中心には儒烏風亭らでんの名前も記載されています。
Juufuutei Raden's name is also inscribed
in the center of the saucer.
最近らでんも紅茶飲めるようになったんで、
お揃いにしましょうや。
Raden has recently started drinking tea too,
so let's have matching ones.
そして、そのお隣がスカーフ。
And the one next to it is the scarf.
新たに書き下ろしたイラスト要素を組み合わせ、ファッション性と実用性を兼ね備えたデザインスカーフでございます。
Combining newly drawn illustration elements, this design scarf blends style and practicality.
そしてじゃあその隣行くか。アクリルスタンド。本コラボならではの新衣装を身に纏うアクリルスタンドでございます。
Next to it are the acrylic stands. They feature the members in outfits unique to this collaboration.
じゃあ右行こう。キャンバスアート。書き下ろしイラストを使用されるキャンバスアートでございます。
Moving to the right, we have canvas art using the newly drawn illustrations.
その下はトートバッグ。表面には本コラボのために書き下ろされたイラスト、裏面には三点の名画のディテールをあしらったデザインの両面仕様となっています。
Below are tote bags. They feature collab art on the front and details from three famous paintings on the back.
そして最後、ランダムクリアカードになります。全六種のランダムクリアカードで、一部のカードには箔押しデジタルサインと特別メッセージが入っていますよ。
Finally, the random clear cards. There are six types, some including foil-stamped digital signs and messages.
グッズいいでしょう？どれも素敵でしょう？
Great lineup, right? They're all so wonderful!
そしてさらに、グッズだけではございません。
And that's not all—there's more than just merch!
ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボで音声ガイドも収録させていただきました！すごい！
I've recorded an audio guide for the collaboration with the London National Gallery! Amazing!
しかもこちらね、なんとらでんの公式チャンネルにてアップする予定でございますが
What's more, we plan to upload it to my official channel...
詳細は後日公開予定となりますので続報をお待ちください！
...but details will be revealed later, so please stay tuned for more news!
と、グッズとガイドと盛りだくさんなんですが
So, with the merch and the guide, there's a lot going on...
みんな、ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなところか... ごめんなさい！
Everyone, the National Gallery in London, I wonder what kind of place it... Sorry!
ちょっと待って。ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなところか気になりませんか？
Wait a sec. Aren't you curious about what the National Gallery in London is like?
ロンドンの街並み、見てみたくないですか？
Don't you want to see the cityscape of London?
ということで、なんと実はリグロスメンバーでロンドンロケに行ってきました！
Well, believe it or not, the ReGLOSS members actually went to London for a location shoot!
そのロケの様子はリグロスチャンネルなどで後日公開予定となっておりますので、こちらもぜひお楽しみに！
The footage will be released on the ReGLOSS channel and elsewhere later, so please look forward to it!
[Text: ReGLOSSロンドンロケ 詳細は後日公開！]
[Text: ReGLOSS London Location Shoot. Details to be revealed later!]
ということで重大告知その二は、儒烏風亭らでんとロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボでございました！ありがとう！
So, major announcement number two was my collaboration with the London National Gallery! Thank you!
そして今、スタッフさんの方から...どうやら今Xで...
And just now, the staff told me... apparently on X right now...
これXですか？Xでトレンド二位だそうです！すごい！みんなありがとう！
Is this X? I'm told I'm #2 on the trends on X! Amazing! Thank you everyone!
大丈夫かな？トレンド二位に入った理由がらでんちゃんの体力が心配ですでめっちゃ入ってたらどうしようかな
I hope it's okay... What if I'm trending because everyone is so worried about my stamina?
でも今日は、体力もすっからかんになって次の日動けなくなるまで頑張るってらでんは決めたんです。
But today, I've decided to give it my all until I'm completely spent and can't move the next day!
だから今日はみんなもいっぱい、いっぱい楽しんでほしいです。どうですか皆さん、ついてこれてますかー？
So I want everyone to have lots of fun today. How about it, everyone, are you keeping up?!
あ、待ってくださいね。重大発表まだあるんです。まだあるんです。これで終わりじゃないんですよ。
Oh, wait a moment. There are still more major announcements. This isn't the end yet!
しかもライブもまだまだ続きますので、皆さんチャンネルはそのままでですよ。
And what's more, the live will continue for a while longer, so stay tuned to the channel!
では次の曲に行きたいと思います。
Now then, I'd like to move on to the next song.
それではどうぞ。
Here it is.
光のすみか
Dwelling of Light
水面に映った藍 眩しく揺れる
The indigo reflected on the water surface sways dazzlingly
手探りで 探してた 足りない私
I was fumbling about, searching for my incomplete self
ゆっくりと動き出した 何万年も前から
Slowly, it began to move, as if from tens of thousands of years ago
この時を約束されていたみたいにほら
As if this moment had been promised, look
風は歌い 雨は語り たどり着くよ 光のすみかへ
The wind sings, the rain tells a tale; we will reach the dwelling of light
幾重にも 重なってる この 地球の偶然
Layer upon layer, overlapping, this coincidence of the Earth
影の向こう 真実の色 見つけ出すよ 光のすみかを
Beyond the shadows, the color of truth; I will find the dwelling of light
一つでも 欠けていたら きっと出会えてなかったね
If even one thing were missing, we surely wouldn't have met, right?
飛べぬまま 見上げてた 透明な空から
From the transparent sky I looked up at while unable to fly...
透明な空から
From the transparent sky,
真っ直ぐに
Stretching straight,
差し込んだ
shining down,
優しい
the gentle
朝日
morning sun.
過ぎた季節が
The past seasons
歪に削った
warped and carved out
今という瞬き
this moment called 'now'.
どこにも同じものはないの
There is nothing the same anywhere.
ほら
Look,
生きてる証
it's the proof that I'm alive.
風は歌い
The wind sings,
雨は語り
the rain tells a story.
たどり着くよ
I will arrive,
光のすみかへ
at the habitat of light.
幾重にも
Overlapping in many layers,
重なってる
this coincidence
この地球の偶然
of this Earth.
影の向こう
Beyond the shadow,
真実の色
I will find the true color,
見つけ出すよ
and the
光のすみかを
habitat of light.
一つでも
If even one thing
欠けていたら
was missing,
きっと
I definitely
出会えてなかったね
wouldn't have been able to meet you.
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは。
Good evening to everyone watching the live stream.
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで、らでんの小咄、美術解説の時間です！
Although we're mid-concert, it's time for Raden's short story: an art commentary session!
今回ご紹介するのはこちらでん、じゃん！
What I'll be introducing this time is... this! Ta-da!
フィンセント・ファン・ゴッホ、『ひまわり』
Vincent van Gogh's 'Sunflowers'.
見ることができます。
...can see it.
ぜひぜひ行ってみてください！
Please, please go and see it!
あ、また次回。
Ah, see you next time.
はい、ということで、早いもので、次が最後の曲でございますが...
Alright, so, time flies, and the next one is the final song...
なんと、儒烏風亭らでん、新曲をリリースします！
Believe it or not, Juufoo-tei Raden is releasing a new song!
特報です！新曲リリース！
Special announcement! New song release!
タイトルは「ミラクルパレット」！
The title is "Miracle Palette"!
「ミラクルパレット」 本日24時 音源リリース！
[Miracle Palette / Digital Release Today 24:00]
楽曲リリースなんですが、5月18日の0時0分...
Regarding the song release, it's May 18th at 00:00...
なので今日の日付が変わったタイミングでリリースされます。
So it will be released as soon as the date changes today.
5月18日といえば、そう、皆さん大正解、国際博物館の日でございます！
Speaking of May 18th, yes, you're absolutely right, it's International Museum Day!
そんな特別な日にリリース。
Releasing on such a special day.
そして、この配信が終わってすぐ、MVですね...
And, right after this stream ends, the MV...
なんとミュージックビデオが公開されます！
Believe it or not, the music video will be released!
儒烏風亭らでん、初のダンスてんこ盛り、3D MVとなっております。
It's Juufoo-tei Raden's first dance-heavy 3D MV.
そしてこちら、楽曲コンセプトはジャズっぽいね...
And the song concept is a jazzy kind of feel...
感じになっておりまーす！
kind of feel!
ということで、今からライブバージョンのミラクルパレット...
So, I'm going to perform the live version of Miracle Palette now.
披露したいと思います。
I'm going to perform it now.
ダンサーさんカモン！
Dancers, come on!
よろしくお願いします。
Please treat us well.
お願いします。
Please.
はい、ありがとうございます。キラキラしてくれてありがとうございます。
Yes, thank you. Thank you for making it sparkle.
では、聴いてください、ミラクルパレット。
Now, please listen to: Miracle Palette.
ミラクルパレット 作詞・作曲・編曲: 太田晴也 (TOKYO LOGIC)
[Miracle Palette | Lyrics, Comp, & Arr: Seiya Ota (TOKYO LOGIC)]
暗がりステージに立つ 雨傘を携え
Standing on a dark stage, carrying an umbrella
朧に霞む構図 印象 儚く
A dimly hazy composition, an impression so fleeting
始めましょ 雨粒ドローイング
Let's begin, raindrop drawing
キャンヴァスはこの空、この世界
The canvas is this sky, this world
Hop Hop 跳び回る
Hop Hop jumping around
Tap Tap 打ち鳴らす
Tap Tap beating out a sound
Dance Dance ぐるぐる
Dance Dance round and round
いざ ショータイム
Now, showtime
Ladies and Gentlemen, welcome to our magical show!
スポットライトを浴びて
Bathed in the spotlight,
輝きを放つ
emitting a radiance
エンタシスよりプリズム
Rather than entasis, it's a prism;
分光をスタンバイ
standby for spectrum splitting
この鈍色の空に 七色の橋を架けて見せましょう
"Let me show you a seven-colored bridge built across this slate-gray sky"
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Come now, take a close look!
目に映るもの、今を彩るから
Because what reflects in your eyes will color the present moment
大きな絵筆で描き出す
Within the bold perspective drawn with a large paintbrush,
大胆なパースの中 嗚呼
within the bold perspective, ah
びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
The soaking wet stage is a miracle palette
マスカレイドな第二部の開演
The masquerade-like second act begins,
Shall we dance?
モノトーンから極彩色に
From monotone to full color,
アシンメトリーなグラデーションで
with an asymmetrical gradation
夢中になってほしいの
I want you to be infatuated,
雨雲にマーブリング
marbling in the rain clouds
目を奪われたその隙
In that gap when your eyes are stolen,
イリュージョンをスタンバイ
standby for the illusion
ところで皆さん、なくし物はございませんか?
"By the way everyone, did you happen to lose something?"
どなた様もおいでませ！
Welcome, anyone and everyone!
あの手この手で魅了していくから
Because I will captivate you with this trick and that trick
一足お先に まんまと盗みだすわ
One step ahead, I will successfully steal away
あなたの心を
your heart
光を放ちだす きらめきのパレット
A sparkling palette starting to emit light
さてさて！ いよいよ大詰め、クライマックスに向けて...
Well well! Finally heading towards the grand finale, the climax...
...盛り上がってまいりましょう！ Listen!
...let's get excited! Listen!
OK, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1, go on the show!
最大級のキャンヴァスに描き出す
Drawing on the largest scale canvas
誰も見たことのない景色
A scenery that no one has ever seen before
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Come now, take a close look!
次元の壁を超えて閃くから
Because it will flash, transcending the dimensional wall
大きな絵筆で描き出す
Drawing with a large paintbrush
大胆なパースの中 さあ
Within the bold perspective, come now
みんなで大団円 迎えに行こう 嗚呼
Let's all go to welcome the grand finale, ah
びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
The soaking wet stage is a miracle palette
特報 その3
[Breaking News Part 3]
ピクセルミュージアム 新情報
[New Info: Pixel Museum]
ピクセルミュージアム 箱根探訪編 DLC
[DLC: Pixel Museum - Hakone Tanbou-hen]
2026年12月 配信予定
[Released in Dec 2026]
イベント展示のご案内
[Event Exhibit Information]
今回のテーマは… 箱根
[Theme: Hakone]
らでん館長の大好きな箱根にまつわる作品をご用意！
[Works related to Director Raden's beloved Hakone!]
館内もイベント仕様で、箱根の魅力がたっぷり！
[The museum is also in event mode, full of charm!]
もちろん解説はフルボイス！
[Of course, the commentary is full-voice!]
な、な、なんと！
Wh-Wh-What!
昨年6月5日の発売から1年を待たずに...
Before a year has even passed since its release...
『ピクセルミュージアム』の追加DLC、『箱根探訪編』の配信が決定しました！
release of the DLC 'Hakone Tanbou-hen' is decided!
やったー！
Yay!
みんながいっぱいダウンロードしてくれて、いっぱい遊んでくれたおかげです
It's all thanks to everyone playing it so much.
本当にありがとうございます！
Thank you all so much!
今回の舞台は、皆様おなじみの『箱根』でございます
This time, the stage is the familiar 'Hakone'.
前作に引き続き、箱根ガラスの森美術館様に加え
Continuing from before, along with Glass Forest Museum...
今回はポーラ美術館様と小田急箱根様にもご協力いただけることとなりました！
...we'll have help from Pola Museum and Odakyu too!
拍手ー！
Applause!
館長のプライベートルームもイベント仕様にアップデート
The private room will be updated for the event.
箱根の魅力マシマシでお届けいたしますよ。いいでしょう？
We'll deliver it with even more charm. Good, right?
そんな追加DLC『箱根探訪編』は、2026年12月に配信予定
That DLC 'Hakone Tanbou-hen' is out Dec 2026.
京都にて開催されます『BitSummit Drift』にラデピクも登場！
Radepiku will appear at BitSummit Drift in Kyoto!
ラデピクの試遊や、箱根探訪編のキービジュアルポストカードの配布もあるみたいですよ
There will be a demo and postcard distribution!
詳しい情報は公式ホームページとジュピターさんの公式Xを要チェックです
Check the official site and X for more details.
まだまだ嬉しい情報もあるかも？
There might be more happy news to come?
それではリリースまでお楽しみに！
So, please look forward to the release!
はい、そして、そして！ 皆さんお待たせ！
Yes, and, and! Everyone, sorry for the wait!
儒烏風亭らでん100万人記念グッズが発売されます！
The 1 Million Subscribers Goods will be on sale!
ごめんね、今日本当に何か発表が多くて
Sorry, there are really a lot of announcements today.
1つ目はこちら。デン！ 『新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック』
First is this: 'New Outfit Live! Acrylic Block'
ライブステージで楽しそうに歌う新衣装のらでん。森倉円先生の描き下ろしでございます
Raden in her new outfit, drawn by En Morikura!
アクリルブロックの表裏に印刷されて、めっちゃ奥行きが感じられるんですよ
It's printed on both sides, so there's great depth.
続いてはこちら。デン！
Next is this one. Ta-da!
『らでんの衣装いろいろ 3連連結アクリルキーホルダー』
'Raden's Various Outfits: 3-Link Acrylic Keychain'
新衣装、通常衣装、ブラッシュアップ衣装の3連連結となっております
It features the new, regular, and brushed-up outfits.
イラストは、ちぽみるく先生でございます
The illustration is by Chipomilk-sensei!
続いてこちら。デン！ 『新衣装モチーフ ピンバッジセット』
Next is this: 'New Outfit Motif Pin Badge Set'
懐中時計、マスク、シルクハット、モノクルの4種類となっております
It features a watch, mask, top hat, and monocle.
続いてはこちら。デン！
Next is this one. Ta-da!
『ライブ前のトラブル！？ボイス』
'Trouble Before the Live!? Voice'
何が起こるのかは聞いてみてな。お楽しみ！
Listen to find out what happens. Look forward to it!
そして、フルセット購入特典はこちら。デン！
And here are the full set purchase bonuses. Ta-da!
はい。儒烏風亭らでん直筆サイン入り、森倉円先生描き下ろしポストカード。
Yes. A postcard signed by Juufutei Raden,
illustrated by Morikura En-sensei.
今回も購入した方全員に直筆でサインを書かせていただきますよ。
I'll be personally signing them for everyone
who purchases this time as well.
皆さんに届くように精一杯書かせていただくので、
I'll put my heart into signing them
so they reach all of you,
よろしくお願いいたします！
so please look forward to it!
さらに、特典ボイスも付きます。
Additionally, bonus voices will be included.
こちらもらでんが書き下ろしてます。
These were also written by Raden.
はい、ということで。今日ね、もうすごい盛りだくさんでございましたが、
Yes, so. Today was really quite a packed schedule,
皆さん追いつけてますか？
are you all keeping up?
結構とんでもないね、発表たくさんしたんですけれども、
We've made quite a lot of incredible announcements,
らでんが一番結構とんでもないなと思っております。
but I think Raden is the most incredible of all.
本日の重大発表は、その1、東京国立博物館さんとのコラボ。
Today's major announcements: Number 1,
a collaboration with Tokyo National Museum.
その2、ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ。
Number 2, a collaboration with
the National Gallery, London.
その3、儒烏風亭らでんがご案内「Pixel Museum」DLC発売決定でございます。
Number 3, the 'Pixel Museum' DLC
guided by Juufutei Raden is confirmed!
情報量が多すぎたと思うので、ぜひアーカイブでも確認してみてください。
It was a lot of info, so please
check the archive as well.
そしてこの後は、メン限でアンコールライブあります。
And after this, we'll have an encore
live for members only.
その時にまた衣装はね、ゆっくりお見せしようかなと思っております。
I'll take the time to show off the outfit properly then.
気になると言う方はメンバーで、またアンコールライブでお会いしましょう。
If you're interested, join as a member
and see you at the encore live!
そしてそして！忘れちゃいけません。
And also! We mustn't forget.
この後すぐ、新曲MV公開でございます！
The new song's MV will be released
right after this!
頑張って作ったんで、いっぱい見てほしいです！
We worked hard on it, so please watch it a lot!
日頃応援してくださっている皆々様、見て、聞いてくださっている、
To everyone who supports me,
and to everyone watching and listening,
リスナーの皆様のおかげで、このライブを開催することができました。
it's thanks to all of you that we
could hold this live stream.
本当に、本当に、ありがとうございます！とっても嬉しいです。
Thank you so, so much! I'm very happy.
これからも歌もダンスも、やりたいことも、いっぱい頑張っていきます。
I'll keep doing my best with singing,
dancing, and everything I want to do.
ぜひ応援のほど、よろしくお願いいたします。
So please continue to support me.
それでは、メン限アンコールライブでお会いいたしましょう。
Well then, let's meet at the
members-only encore live!
本日のお相手は私、儒烏風亭らでんでございました。
Today's host was me, Juufutei Raden.
それでは皆さん、良い夜をお過ごしください。さようならで〜ん！
Well then, everyone, have a wonderful night.
Sayonara-den!